<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-homburg-dnsop-codcp-00" submissionType="IETF" category="std" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" indexInclude="true" consensus="true">

<front>
<title abbrev="codcp">Control Options For DNS Client Proxies</title><seriesInfo value="draft-homburg-dnsop-codcp-00" stream="IETF" status="standard" name="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
<author initials="P.C." surname="Homburg" fullname="Philip Homburg"><organization></organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>philip@nlnetlabs.nl</email>
</address></author><date/>
<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>DNSOP</workgroup>

<abstract>
<t>The introduction of many new transport protocols for DNS in recent years
(DoT, DoH, DoQ)
significantly increases the complexity of DNS stub
resolvers that want to support these protocols. A practical way forward
is to have a DNS client proxy in the host operating system. This allows
applications to communicate using Do53 and still get the privacy
benefit from using more secure protocols over the internet. However,
such a setup leaves the application with no control over which transport
the proxy uses. This document introduces EDNS(0) options that allow a
stub resolver to request certain transport and allow the proxy to report
capabilities and actual transports that are available.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="definitions"><name>Definitions</name>

<dl>
<dt>Do53</dt>
<dd><t>The original, plain text DNS transport as described in <xref target="RFC1034"></xref><xref target="RFC1035"></xref>.
Typically, UDP is used, with the DNS server listening on port 53. Sometimes,
for example, for large responses, TCP is used, also on port 53.</t>
</dd>
<dt>DoH</dt>
<dd><t>DNS over HTTPS as described in <xref target="RFC8484"></xref>.</t>
</dd>
<dt>DoT</dt>
<dd><t>DNS over TLS as described in <xref target="RFC7858"></xref></t>
</dd>
<dt>DoQ</dt>
<dd><t>DNS over QUIC (<xref target="RFC9000"></xref>) as described in [I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsoquic],
not to be confused with DNS over HTTP/3 which also uses QUIC</t>
</dd>
<dt>EDNS(0) Option</dt>
<dd><t>An option as described in <xref target="RFC6891"></xref></t>
</dd>
<dt>h2</dt>
<dd><t>This TLS ALPN identifies HTTP/2 as described in <xref target="RFC7540"></xref></t>
</dd>
<dt>h3</dt>
<dd><t>This TLS ALPN identifies HTTP/3, which is HTTP over QUIC and
is described in I.D.ietf-quic-http (expired draft)</t>
</dd>
<dt>Interface Name</dt>
<dd><t>A name that identifies a network interface as described in <xref target="RFC3493"></xref>.
In addition, an interface index converted to a decimal number is also
consider an interface name.</t>
</dd>
<dt>PKIX</dt>
<dd><t>Public-Key Infrastructure using X.509. See <xref target="RFC5280"></xref></t>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>
<t>The introduction of many new transport protocols for DNS in recent years
(DoT, DoH, DoQ)
significantly increases the complexity of DNS stub
resolvers that want to support these protocols. In addition,
for short-lived applications, the overhead of setting a DoH connection
is quite high if the application only needs to send a few DNS requests.</t>
<t>A practical way forward
is to have a DNS client proxy in the host operating system.
A local proxy may provide some benefit to short-lived applications by
caching results. In particular if the system uses a so called 'public
DNS resolver'. In general we assume that the cache is tagged according
to the source of a reply and the transport it is received on.</t>
<t>This allows
applications to communicate using Do53 and still get the privacy
benefits from using more secure protocols over the internet. However,
such a setup leaves the application with no control over which transport
the proxy uses. This document introduces EDNS(0) options that allow a
stub resolver to request certain transports and allow the proxy to report
capabilities and actual transports that are available.</t>
<t>With respect to DNSSEC, we assume that an application that needs
DNSSEC validation, for example, for DANE validation or SSHFP, will
perform the DNSSEC validation within the application itself and does not
trust the proxy. The proxy can of course do DNSSEC validation as well.
Important however, is that an untrusted proxy cannot provide an application
with a traditional (unsigned) trust anchor.</t>
<t>For the transport configuration we expect three levels of details. The
first is a choice between requiring authenticated encryption, also allowing unauthenticated encryption or doing opportunistic encryption on an best effort basis. The second level is where the application also
specifies the names and/or IP addresses of upstream resolvers. The
third level is where the application also specifies which transports
(Do53, DoT, DoH, DoQ) are allowed to be used. A final transport parameter
is the outgoing interface that is to be used.</t>
<t>For authentication we can have a mix of PKIX and DANE. Options are one of
the two and not the other, both or one of the two.</t>
<t>In a response, the proxy reports the interface, resolver, and transport
used.</t>
<t>As described in <xref target="RFC5625" sectionFormat="bare" relative="#" section="Section 3"></xref> of <xref target="RFC5625"></xref>, some simple DNS proxies
may just forward DNS packets without handling of EDNS(0) options.
So what could happen is that an application sends a privacy sensitive
request to local proxy,
expecting the proxy upstream connection to be encrypted. However, a simple
proxy may just forward the request unencrypted to another proxy, for example,
one in a CPE that does implement the protocol described in this document. So
what could happen is that the request travels unencrypted over a local lan,
or if proxies deeper in the network support this protocol, even further
without the application noticing that something is wrong.</t>
<t>To handle this case, we introduce an option where the proxy reports
whether the connection between the stub resolver and the proxy is
host-local, link-local, or site-local or global.</t>
<t>In the ideal case, the host operating system provides applications with a
secure way to access a DNSSEC trust anchor that is maintained according to
<xref target="RFC5011"></xref>. However in situations where this is not the case, an application
can fall back to <xref target="RFC7958"></xref>. However, for short lived processes, there is
considerable overhead in issuing two HTTP(S) requests to data.iana.org to
obtain the trust anchor XML file and the signature over the trust anchor.
For this reason, it makes sense to let the proxy cache this information.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="key-words"><name>Key Words</name>
<t>The key words &quot;<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>&quot;,
&quot;<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>&quot;, &quot;<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>&quot;, and
&quot;<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref>
when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="description"><name>Description</name>
<t>This document introduces three new EDNS(0) options, and one new response code.
This first option, called PROXY CONTROL Option, specifies which transports
a proxy should use to connect to a recursive resolver.</t>
<t>The second option, called PROXY SCOPE Option, reports the IP address scope
of the connection between the application's stub resolver and the proxy.</t>
<t>Finally, the TRUST ANCHOR Option, provides the application with a DNSSEC
trust anchor signed by IANA.</t>
<t>The BADPROXYPOLICY error is returned the proxy cannot meet the requirements
in a PROXY CONTROL Option or the option is malformed.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="proxy-control-option"><name>PROXY CONTROL OPTION</name>

<artwork>      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   0: |                          OPTION-CODE                          |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   2: |                         OPTION-LENGTH                         |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   4: ~                 Type-Length-Value (TLV) Options               ~
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
<t>where</t>

<dl newline="true">
<dt>OPTION-CODE</dt>
<dd><t>To be decided</t>
</dd>
<dt>OPTION-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>Length of this option excluding the OPTION-CODE and OPTION-LENGTH fields</t>
</dd>
</dl>
<t>The remainer is filled with a collection of TLV sub-options defined next.
All sub-options have the following format:</t>

<artwork>      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   0: |                      SUB-OPTION-CODE                          |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   2: |                     SUB-OPTION-LENGTH                         |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   4: ~                      Sub-Option Data                          ~
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
<t>where</t>

<dl newline="true">
<dt>SUB-OPTION-CODE</dt>
<dd><t>To be decided</t>
</dd>
<dt>SUB-OPTION-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>Length of this sub-option excluding the SUB-OPTION-CODE and
SUB-OPTION-LENGTH fields</t>
</dd>
<dt>Sub-Option Data</dt>
<dd><t>Sub-option specific data</t>
</dd>
</dl>

<section anchor="security-flags-sub-option"><name>Security Flags Sub-option</name>

<artwork>      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   0: |                      SUB-OPTION-CODE                          |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   2: |                     SUB-OPTION-LENGTH                         |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   4: | U |UA | A | P | D |                         Z                 |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>
<t>where</t>

<dl newline="true">
<dt>SUB-OPTION-CODE</dt>
<dd><t>To be decided</t>
</dd>
<dt>SUB-OPTION-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>2 (this option defines a 16-bit flags field</t>
</dd>
<dt>U</dt>
<dd><t>force the use of unencrypted communication (Do53)</t>
</dd>
<dt>UA</dt>
<dd><t>require unauthenticated encryption</t>
</dd>
<dt>A</dt>
<dd><t>require authenticated encryption</t>
</dd>
<dt>P</dt>
<dd><t>authenticate using a PKIX certificate</t>
</dd>
<dt>D</dt>
<dd><t>authenticate using DANE</t>
</dd>
<dt>Z</dt>
<dd><t>reserved, MUST be zero when sending, MUST be ignored when received</t>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="transport-priority-sub-option"><name>Transport Priority Sub-option</name>

<artwork>      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   0: |                      SUB-OPTION-CODE                          |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   2: |                     SUB-OPTION-LENGTH                         |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   4: | TRANSPORT PROTOCOL            |        PRIORITY               |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>
<t>where</t>

<dl newline="true">
<dt>SUB-OPTION-CODE</dt>
<dd><t>To be decided</t>
</dd>
<dt>SUB-OPTION-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>2</t>
</dd>
<dt>TRANSPORT PROTOCOL</dt>
<dd><t>A DNS transport protocol idenfier. The value 0 is used to specify any
transport implemented by server.</t>
</dd>
<dt>PRIORITY</dt>
<dd><t>The priority of this transport relative to other transports. The value 0
indicates the highest priority and 254 the lowest. The value 255 is
reserved to mean that this protocol MUST NOT be used.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="domain-name"><name>Domain Name</name>

<artwork>      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   0: |                      SUB-OPTION-CODE                          |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   2: |                     SUB-OPTION-LENGTH                         |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   4: ~                        DOMAIN NAME                            ~
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>
<t>where</t>

<dl newline="true">
<dt>SUB-OPTION-CODE</dt>
<dd><t>To be decided</t>
</dd>
<dt>SUB-OPTION-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>Length of this sub-option excluding the SUB-OPTION-CODE and
SUB-OPTION-LENGTH fields</t>
</dd>
<dt>DOMAIN NAME</dt>
<dd><t>domain name for authentication or resolving IP addresses. The domain name
is encoded in uncompressed DNS wire format.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="svc-parameter"><name>SVC Parameter</name>

<artwork>      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   0: |                      SUB-OPTION-CODE                          |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   2: |                     SUB-OPTION-LENGTH                         |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   4: |                       SVCPARAM KEY                            |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   6: ~                         SVCPARAM                              ~
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>
<t>where</t>

<dl newline="true">
<dt>SUB-OPTION-CODE</dt>
<dd><t>To be decided</t>
</dd>
<dt>SUB-OPTION-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>Length of this sub-option excluding the SUB-OPTION-CODE and
SUB-OPTION-LENGTH fields</t>
</dd>
<dt>SVCPARAM KEY</dt>
<dd><t>Key of Svc parameters as defined in [ref]</t>
</dd>
<dt>SvcParam</dt>
<dd><t>Svc parameter value</t>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="interface-name"><name>Interface Name</name>

<artwork>      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   0: |                      SUB-OPTION-CODE                          |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   2: |                     SUB-OPTION-LENGTH                         |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   4: ~                      INTERFACE NAME                           ~
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>
<t>where</t>

<dl newline="true">
<dt>SUB-OPTION-CODE</dt>
<dd><t>To be decided</t>
</dd>
<dt>SUB-OPTION-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>Length of this sub-option excluding the SUB-OPTION-CODE and
SUB-OPTION-LENGTH fields</t>
</dd>
<dt>INTERFACE NAME</dt>
<dd><t>name of outgoing interface for transport connections</t>
</dd>
</dl>
<t>This option is designed to give control over what level of detail it
wants to specify. The first 5 flags (U, UA, A, P, and D) give general
requirements for properties of DNS transports that are used by the
client proxy.
The U, UA, and A flags are mutually exclusive. If more than one
flag is set, the proxy SHOULD return a BADPROXYPOLICY error.
There are four possibilities:</t>

<dl>
<dt>U = 0, UA = 0, A = 0</dt>
<dd><t>An effort is made to reach authenticated encryption, if that fails,
unauthenticated encryption is tried. If that also fails, the proxy
resorts to an unencrypted transport.
It is an error
if either or both of the P or D flags is set and the proxy SHOULD
return a BADPROXYPOLICY error.</t>
</dd>
<dt>U = 1, UA = 0, A = 0</dt>
<dd><t>The proxy only tries only unencrypted transports.
It is an error
if either or both of the P or D flags is set and the proxy SHOULD return a
BADPROXYPOLICY error.</t>
</dd>
<dt>U = 0, UA = 1, A = 0</dt>
<dd><t>An effort is made to reach authenticated encryption, if that fails,
unauthenticated encryption is tried.
It is an error
if either or both of the P or D flags is set and the proxy SHOULD return a
BADPROXYPOLICY error.</t>
</dd>
<dt>U = 0, UA = 0, A = 1</dt>
<dd><t>The proxy only tries authenticated encryption. The P and D flags can be
set to control which authentication mechanism has to be used.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
<t>The P and D flags allow the application to require
a specific authentication mechanism (PKIX or DANE). The meaning of the
flags is the following:</t>

<dl>
<dt>P = 0, D = 0</dt>
<dd><t>At least one of the two mechanisms has to validate for authenticated
encryption to succeed.</t>
</dd>
<dt>P = 1, D = 0</dt>
<dd><t>PKIX validation has to succeed, the status of DANE validation is ignored.</t>
</dd>
<dt>P = 0, D = 1</dt>
<dd><t>A DANE record has to be present and be DNSSEC valid.
A DANE record has
a Certificate Usage Field. For some values of this field (the values zero
and one), DANE requires PKIX validation.
In those cases, PKIX validation is also required according to the DANE
specifications. For the values two and three, DANE does not require
PKIX and because the P flag is zero, the result of PKIX validation has to
be ignored.</t>
</dd>
<dt>P = 1, D = 1</dt>
<dd><t>Both PKIX and DANE are required together. For PKIX, this means that
PKIX validation has to succeed. For DANE it means that a DANE record
has to be present and be DNSSEC valid. Validation using the DANE record
has to succeed.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
<t>Note that these two flags can only be used in combination with the A
flag. The proxy SHOULD return a BADPROXYPOLICY error if either or both of the
P or D flags is set and the A flag is clear.</t>
<t>The next flags provide more detailed control over which transports
should be used or not. For each of 5 different transports
(Do53, DoT, DoH with ALPN h2, DoH with ALPN h3, DoQ) there is a flag
to allow (A53,AT,AH2,AH3,AQ) or disallow (D53,DT,DH2,DH3,DQ) the use of the
transport. There is space to add more transports later. Note that setting
the A flag and the D flag for a protocol (for example, setting both the
A53 and the D53 flags) is not allowed and a proxy SHOULD reject such a request.</t>
<t>To future proof applications, there is a single flag DD, that by default
disallows transports that are not explicitly listed. With this flag clear,
the application allows all transports that are not explicitly disallowed
(including future transports). With the flag set, the
application has to explicitly list which transports can be used.
For example, by setting only DD and AT, the application forces the
use of DoT.</t>
<t>When DD = 0:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>all transports are in the pool of potentially usable transports</li>
<li>D53, DT, DH2, DH3 and DQ remove those transports from the pool.</li>
<li>The values of A53, AT, AH2, AH3 and AQ are irrelevant</li>
</ul>
<t>When DD = 1:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>no transports are in the pool of potentially usable transports</li>
<li>A53, AT, AH2, AH3 and AQ add those transports to the pool</li>
<li>The values of D53, DT, DH2, DH3 and DQ are irrelevant</li>
</ul>
<t>Finally, an application can specify its own resolvers or rely on the
resolvers that are known to the proxy. If ADN Length and Addr Length
are both zero, then the application requests the resolvers known to
the proxy. [Note: it is unclear at the moment what to do with any
Service Parameters]</t>
<t>If the application specifies only an authentication-domain-name then the
proxy is expected to resolve the name to addresses. If only addresses
are specified then the proxy assumes that no name is known (though
a PKIX certificate may include an address literal in the subjectAltName).
If both a name and address are specified then the proxy will use the
specified address and use the name for authentication.</t>
<t>To simplify the encoding of the option, an option with addresses will
have either IPv4 or IPv6 addresses. If the application wants to specify
both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses for a certain authentication-domain-name
then it has to include two options.</t>
<t>An application may want to specify a DNS resolver that is reachable
through an IPv6 link-local address.
IPv6 link-local addresses are special in that they require a zone to be
specified, either explicitly or implicitly. Typically for a link-local
address that appears as a source or destination address,
the zone is implicitly the zone of the link the packet travels on.
For packets that travel between hosts, there is no goed way to explictly
specify the zone of a link-local address because two different hosts
do not agree on zone names. However, if the proxy is on the same host
as the application, then the zone identifier for the link-local address
can be specified in the Interface field. For this purpose an interface
name can also be an interface index expressed as a decimal string.</t>
<t>When present, Service Parameters specify how to connect. Otherwise it is
up to the proxy to try various possibilities. For Service Parameters,
the values of the ipv4hint and ipv6hint fields are ignored. Addresses
can only be specified using the addresses field in the PROXY CONTROL Option.</t>
<t>Associated with this option is a new error, BADPROXYPOLICY. When
a proxy cannot meet the requirements in a PROXY CONTROL Option or the
option is malformed, it returns this error.</t>
<t>If the proxy returns a BADPROXYPOLICY error, the proxy MAY include
a PROXY CONTROL Option that lists what the proxy can do. For example,
if authenticated encryption is not possible, but unauthenticated is,
then the proxy may include an option that has the UA bit set.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="proxy-scope-option"><name>PROXY SCOPE OPTION</name>

<artwork>      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   0: |                          OPTION-CODE                          |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   2: |                         OPTION-LENGTH                         |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   4: |                          Scope                                |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
</artwork>

<dl newline="true">
<dt>OPTION-CODE</dt>
<dd><t>To be decided</t>
</dd>
<dt>OPTION-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>Length of this option excluding the OPTION-CODE and OPTION-LENGTH fields</t>
</dd>
<dt>Scope</dt>
<dd><t>Scope of the source address of a request. Scope can have the following
values:</t>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Value</th>
<th>Scope</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>0</td>
<td>Undefined</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Host local</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>2</td>
<td>Link local</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Site local</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>4</td>
<td>Global</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></dd>
</dl>
<t>The purpose of this option is to deal with proxies that forward
DNS traffic without first removing any EDNS(0) options. The option requests
the DNS proxy that processes the option to report the scope of the source
address.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="trust-anchor-option"><name>TRUST ANCHOR OPTION</name>

<artwork>      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   0: |                          OPTION-CODE                          |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   2: |                         OPTION-LENGTH                         |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   4: |             ANCHORS-XML-LENGTH                                |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   6: ~             ANCHORS-XML                                       ~
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   4: |             ANCHORS-P7S-LENGTH                                |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
   6: ~             ANCHORS-P7S                                       ~
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
<t>where</t>

<dl newline="true">
<dt>OPTION-CODE</dt>
<dd><t>To be decided</t>
</dd>
<dt>OPTION-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>Length of this option excluding the OPTION-CODE and OPTION-LENGTH fields</t>
</dd>
<dt>ANCHORS-XML-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>Length of ANCHORS-XML in network byte order</t>
</dd>
<dt>ANCHORS-XML</dt>
<dd><t>Trust anchors in XML format</t>
</dd>
<dt>ANCHORS-P7S-LENGTH</dt>
<dd><t>Length of ANCHORS-P7S in network byte order</t>
</dd>
<dt>ANCHORS-P7S</dt>
<dd><t>Signature in p7s format</t>
</dd>
</dl>
<t>This option provides DNSSEC trust anchors as described in <xref target="RFC7958"></xref>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="protocol-specification"><name>Protocol Specification</name>

<section anchor="client-processing"><name>Client Processing</name>
<t>A stub resolver that wishes to use the PROXY CONTROL Option includes the
option in all outgoing DNS requests that require privacy. The option
should be initialized according to the needs of the application.
In addition the PROXY SCOPE Option can be added. In requests, the Scope
field is set to undefined.</t>
<t>If the stub resolver receives a reply without a PROXY CONTROL Option
included in the reply, then stub resolver has to assume that traffic will
have Do53 levels of privacy.  Similarly, a lack of a PROXY SCOPE Option
implies a global scope.</t>
<t>If the stub resolver receives a BADPROXYPOLICY error then the proxy was
unable to meet the requirements of the PROXY CONTROL Option.</t>

<section anchor="probing"><name>Probing</name>
<t>In cases where the stub resolver expects a local DNS proxy, or where the
stub resolver has (a limited) fall back to more private transports, or
when the security policy of the application is such that is better to fail
than send queries over Do53, the stub resolver first sends a probing
query to verify that the proxy supports the PROXY CONTROL and
PROXY SCOPE Options.</t>
<t>This request queries &quot;resolver.arpa&quot; for SOA records.
The proxy MUST implement this as a
Special Use Domain Name. The actual response is not important. The
important part is that the proxy returns PROXY CONTROL and PROXY SCOPE
Options as described in this document or sets
the response code to BADPROXYPOLICY if it cannot meet specified policy.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="trust-anchor"><name>Trust Anchor</name>
<t>In the ideal case, the host operating system provides applications with a
secure way to access a DNSSEC trust anchor that is maintained according to
<xref target="RFC5011"></xref>. However in situations where this is not the case, an application
can fall back to <xref target="RFC7958"></xref>. However, for short lived processes, there is
considerable overhead in issuing two HTTP(S) requests to data.iana.org to
obtain the trust anchor XML file and the signature over the trust anchor.
For this reason, it makes sense to let the proxy cache this information.</t>
<t>If the local operating system does not provide a DNSSEC trust anchor, then
the application can ask the proxy. The stub resolver adds the TRUST ANCHOR
Option with ANCHORS-XML-LENGTH and ANCHORS-P7S-LENGTH set to zero. If the
proxy returns both an ANCHORS-XML and an ANCHORS-P7S, then the application
verifies the trust anchor using the trust anchor certificate (which needs
to come with the application).</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="server-processing"><name>Server Processing</name>
<t>Proxies are encouraged to cache options that appear in requests under the
assumption that a stub resolver will send multiple requests. If a proxy
caches DNS responses then the proxy MUST tag cached responses with the
properties of the DNS transport. When responding to later requests,
the proxy returns a cached entry only if the parameters of the DNS transport
match what is specified in the request.</t>
<t>When a proxy receives a new set of requirements, the proxy compiles a list of
addresses to connect to and a list of transports to try per address.
The proxy SHOULD prefer more private transports over less private ones.</t>
<t>If the proxy cannot obtain a connection to a recursive resolver in a way that
matches the provided policy, then the proxy sets the BADPROXYPOLICY
response code in the reply.</t>
<t>The proxy MUST implement &quot;resolver.arpa&quot; as a locally served zone.
Proxies SHOULD respond to all queries with NODATA unless other behavior
is specified in a different document.</t>
<t>If the proxy successfully connects to a recursive resolver and receives a
reply, or the query is for a special use domain name that is handled internally
in the proxy, then the proxy add a PROXY CONTROL Options dat details the
connection to the recursive resolver (i.e., the U, UA, or A flag depending
on encryption and authentication, P and or D for authenticated connections,
A53, AT, AH2, AH3, or AQ depending on the transport (or none of those for a
future transport). Furthermore the proxy includes the address it
connected to, the Domain Name if known, any Service Parameters and
the outgoing interface name if known.</t>
<t>If the proxy finds a PROXY SCOPE Option, then it calculates the scope from
the source address. The proxy adds a PROXY SCOPE Option to a reply and
sets the value of Scope to the actual scope of the source address of the
request.</t>
<t>If the request contains a TRUST ANCHOR Option, then the proxy tries to
fetch the trust anchor XML and p7s files if it does not have them already.
If fetching one or both fails then the proxy sets the corresponding
length to zero. It is not clear how long the proxy can cache this information.
<xref target="RFC7958"></xref> Does not describe how long these documents can be cache.
A simple solution is to take the Expires header in the HTTP reply.
The proxy adds a TRUST ANCHOR Option to the reply.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="connection-between-stub-resolver-and-proxy"><name>Connection Between Stub Resolver And Proxy</name>
<t>Absent other configuration, a stub resolver that implements this standard
SHOULD connect to the proxy using Do53 and as remote address either ::1 or
127.0.0.1. In particular, the stub resolver SHOULD avoid using name
servers listed in files such as /etc/resolv.conf.</t>
<t>The reason for this is to simplify the integration of local DNS proxies
in existing environments. If the stub resolver ignores /etc/resolv.conf
then the proxy can use that information to connect to recursive resolvers.</t>
<t>If no DNS server is responding to queries sent using Do53 to ::1 and 127.0.0.1,
or if the response indicates that this standard is not supported, then
the stub resolver MAY fall back to traditional configuration methods, such
as /etc/resolv.conf. However, in that case the stub resolver MUST make
sure that doing so does not violate the policy set by the application.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations"><name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>A privacy sensitive application SHOULD first issue a SOA query for
resolver.arpa to verify that the local proxy supports the options documented
in the document. If the proxy does not support this document then the
application can refrain from sending queries that reveal privacy sensitive
names.</t>
<t>By setting the interface name, an application can select an outging interface
on the proxy. Proxies should make sure that a query receives from a
process that is authorized to do so. By default, a proxy SHOULD allow only
process on the same host to use this feature. If an unauthorized process
includes an option with the interface name set, then the proxy SHOULD
return the BADPROXYPOLICY error.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
<t>IANA has assigned the following DNS EDNS0 option codes:</t>

<artwork> Value   Name           Status     Reference
------- -------------- ---------- -----------
 TBD     PROXY CONTROL  Standard   RFC xxxx
 TBD     PROXY SCOPE    Standard   RFC xxxx
 TBD     TRUST ANCHOR   Standard   RFC xxxx
</artwork>
<t>IANA has assigned the following Extended DNS Error code:</t>

<artwork> INFO-CODE   Name             Purpose                       Reference
----------- ---------------- ----------------------------- -----------
 TBD         BADPROXYPOLICY   Unable to conform to policy   RFC xxxx
</artwork>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements"><name>Acknowledgements</name>
<t>Many thanks to Yorgos Thessalonikefs and Willem Toorop for their feedback.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
</references>
<references><name>Informative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3493.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5011.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5625.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6891.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7540.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7858.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7958.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8484.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9000.xml"/>
</references>

<section anchor="change-history"><name>Change history</name>
<t>(This section to be removed by the RFC editor.)</t>

<ul>
<li><t>draft-homburg-dnsop-codcp-00</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Renamed to draft-homburg-dnsop-codcp</li>
<li>IANA section with allocated code points</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>draft-homburg-add-codcp-00</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Initial version</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
